Hey, welcome to The Explainer.
こんにちは、ようこそ
Today, we're gonna put on our detective hats
今日は探偵の帽子をかぶって
and solve this really curious grammar puzzle,
興味深い文法の謎を解きます
one that's hiding in plain sight.
それは目の前に隠れています
Okay, so every good case has to start with a mystery, right? And ours?
良い事件は謎から始まりますよね？私たちの謎は？
Well, it's all about a simple, super common word
とても一般的な単語についてです
that just doesn't seem to play by the rules. So, take a look at this.
でも、ルールに従っていないようです。これを見てください
On one side, you've got a broken toy. Totally normal, right?
一方には壊れたおもちゃがあります。普通ですよね？
But then on the other side, a toy broken by my brother.
でも、もう一方には兄が壊したおもちゃがあります
It's basically the same idea. But wait a second. Look what happened.
基本的には同じアイデアです。でも、ちょっと待ってください
Our main word, broken, completely jumped to a new spot.
私たちの主な単語、brokenが全く別の位置に移動しました。
What's up with that? Yeah, why?
どういうこと？なぜでしょう？
Why does it just decide to hop from before the noun to after it?
なぜ名詞の前から後ろに移動するのでしょう？
This weird little inconsistency,
この不思議な不一致が
that is the exact puzzle we are gonna solve together today.
今日一緒に解決する謎です
All right, so the key to cracking this whole thing
さて、この謎を解く鍵は
wide open is getting to know our main suspect.
私たちの主な容疑者を知ることです
It's a special verb form and it's called the past participle.
それは特別な動詞の形で、過去分詞と呼ばれます
Now to really understand our suspect,
この容疑者を理解するためには
You gotta look at its background, right?
その背景を見なければなりません
So most verbs have these three main forms.
動詞には3つの主要な形があります
You've got the present, like break, then the simple past, broke,
現在形のbreak、次に過去形のbroke
and then there's this third form, the past participle,
そしてこの3つ目の形、過去分詞
broken, and that's the one we're zeroing in on.
brokenが私たちの焦点です
Okay, so here's the absolute crucial point.
さて、ここが重要なポイントです
A past participle, it has what we call a passive meaning.
過去分詞は受動的な意味を持っています
This means it's not describing the noun doing an action.
つまり、名詞が行動をするのではなく
Nope, it's describing an action that was done to it.
何かをされたということを表しています
So, you know, the toy didn't break something, It was broken.
おもちゃは何かを壊すのではなく、壊されたのです
See the difference? Okay, time to check out our first big clue.
違いがわかりますか？さて、最初の大きな手がかりを見てみましょう
This is gonna show us what happens
これが何が起こるかを示します
when our past participle is what I like to call a lone wolf
過去分詞が孤独な狼のように働くときです
when it's working completely by itself. And you know what?
完全に一人で働いているときです。実は
The rule is so simple, it's great.
ルールはとてもシンプルです
When the past participle is just that one single word,
過去分詞が単独の単語の場合
it acts exactly like a regular adjective.
普通の形容詞のように振る舞います
You know, like a red car or a big house. It just pops right in there
赤い車や大きな家のように、名詞の前に入ります
before the noun it's describing.
見れば、このパターンは至る所にあります
And once you see it, you'll see this pattern absolutely everywhere.
broken toy, used car, stolen money boiled egg, わかりますか？
A broken toy, a used car, stolen money, a boiled egg, see?
その分詞だけのときは、常に最初に来ます
When that participle is flying solo, it always comes first.
シンプルで、クリーンで、一貫しています
It's simple. It's clean. It's super consistent.
でも、私たちの主な容疑者はいつも一人で働くわけではありません
But our main suspect doesn't always work alone.
そうではないので、友達を連れてくるとどうなるか見てみましょう
Uh-uh, so let's see what happens when it decides to bring some friends along for
一緒にグループの一部になるときです。そして、これが
the ride when it's part of a whole gang. And this, right here.
私たちの謎の大きなひねりです。brokenはいつも孤独な狼ではありません
This is the big twist in our mystery, because broken isn't always a lone wolf.
時には仲間と一緒にやってきて、それが全てを変えます
Sometimes it rolls up with a crew, and that, that just changes the entire game.
さて、普通の例から始めてみましょう
Okay, let's just start with a normal example to see what I mean.
「面白い本」です
An interesting book.
形容詞のinterestingは一つの単語です
The adjective interesting is just one word, right? A lone wolf.
だから本の前に来ます。これがルール1の実践です
So it comes before book. That's our rule number one in action.
さて、同じ論理を過去分詞のフレーズに適用してみましょう
Okay, now let's try that same logic with a past participle phrase.
主な単語はwrittenですが、その仲間はin Englishです
The main word is written, but its gang is in English.
もしルール1を使おうとしたら
Now, if we tried to use rule number one,
written in English book となりますが
we'd say something like a written in English book.
でも、それはおかしいですよね？
And that just sounds wrong, doesn't it?
それは、グループ全体が一緒にいる必要があるからです
That's because the whole group, the whole gang, has to stick together.
これがルール2につながります
So, that brings us to a rule number two.
このルールも最初のルールと同じくらい重要です
And this one is just as important as the first.
全体の説明的なフレーズ、それが分詞です
and all its buddies, it has to stick together
そして、仲間たちと一緒に いる必要があります
and it has to come after the noun it's describing.
それは、修飾する名詞の後に 来なければなりません
and you see this pattern playing out consistently.
このパターンは一貫して現れます
We don't say a made in Germany car, do we?
made in Germany car とは言いませんよね？
No, we say a car made in Germany. It's not the cooked by Helen meal,
car made in Germany と言います。 cooked by Helen meal ではなく、
it's the meal cooked by Helen. The gang always, always follows.
meal cooked by Helen と言います 仲間は常に後に続きます
So there you have it. With just those two simple rules,
これでわかりましたね。たった二つの シンプルなルールで
we've totally cracked the case.
私たちは完全に解決しました
The mystery of the moving word, it is officially solved.
動く言葉の謎は、正式に解決です
Okay, let's lay out all the evidence.
さて、証拠を整理しましょう
The position of that past participle really just depends on one thing.
過去分詞の位置を決めるのは
Is it flying solo or is it with its gang?
単独なのか、仲間と一緒なのかです
If it's a lone wolf, like broken,
もし孤独な狼のように broken だけなら
it acts just like a regular old adjective and goes before the noun.
普通の形容詞のように名詞の前に 来ます
But if it's with the gang, like in made in Germany,
しかし、仲間と一緒の場合、例えば made in Germany なら
the whole freight has to move to a new spot, after the noun.
全体が名詞の後に移動しなければ なりません
It's that simple, two situations, two rules.
それは簡単なルールです
And that, my friends, is the solution to our puzzle.
これが私たちのパズルの解決策です
And you know, this is really why this little puzzle matters so much.
そして、これがこの小さなパズルが 重要な理由です
It isn't just about being grammatically correct.
文法的に正しいだけではありません
Getting the simple pattern down is a huge key
このシンプルなパターンを理解することは
to making your English sound way more fluid, way more natural.
英語をより流暢で自然に聞こえさせる 大きな鍵です
It's one of those little tiny details
これは実際に大きな違いを生む
that actually makes a massive difference.
小さな詳細の一つです
Solving this really makes you wonder, doesn't it?
これを解決すると、考えさせられますよね？
What other grammar puzzles are just hiding out there in plain sight?
他にどんな文法のパズルが 目の前に隠れているのでしょう？
What other simple rules are just waiting
他にどんなシンプルなルールが
for a good detective to come along and uncover them?
良い探偵が現れるのを待っているのでしょう？